<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Geekology - Technical Recruiting Training]]></title>
  <link href="http://geekology.heroku.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://geekology.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-11T00:43:38-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://geekology.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geekology]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[geekology@jobfully.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is an SDET ?]]></title>
    <link href="http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/02/10/what-is-an-sdet/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-10T23:16:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/02/10/what-is-an-sdet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
If you are a software developer looking for a contract or full-time job with companies like Microsoft, Amazon, etc., you&#8217;ve probably been approached by enough recruiters that asked you if you&#8217;d be interested in working as an SDET. Your first reaction might have been - Testing? No way. <!-- More --> Then, they start talking about how it involves a lot of coding and now you think, &#8220;Now, that&#8217;s different from what I thought about testing.&#8221;
</p>




<p>
If you are a technical recruiter, you might also be a bit unclear about what exactly is a SDET.  You might be wondering, &#8220;Is SDET same as a tester?&#8221;  But, SDETs seem to be requiring just as much coding as software engineers.  Then you ask yourself, &#8220;What skills am I supposed to look for when my hiring manager is looking for a SDET?&#8221;
</p>




<p>
To help demystify SDET, here is a collection of articles that explain what an SDET is and does:
</p>




<ul> 
  <li>
    From Scott Louvau&#8217;s blog on MSDN - <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/scottlo/archive/2005/06/29/434121.aspx">http://blogs.msdn.com/b/scottlo/archive/2005/06/29/434121.aspx</a>
  </li>
 
  <li>From Seth Eliot&#8217;s blogs on msdn</li>
  <ul>
    <li>Part 1 <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/seliot/archive/2010/04/18/what-is-an-sdet.aspx">http://blogs.msdn.com/b/seliot/archive/2010/04/18/what-is-an-sdet.aspx</a></li>
    <li>Part 2 <a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/seliot/archive/2010/04/21/what-is-an-sdet-part-2.aspx">http://blogs.msdn.com/b/seliot/archive/2010/04/21/what-is-an-sdet-part-2.aspx</a></li>
  </ul>

  <li>From a discussion on Stack Exchange <a href="http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/44623/microsofts-software-development-engineer-in-test-position">http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/44623/microsofts-software-development-engineer-in-test-position</a>
  </li>
</ul>




<h2>A Great Summary by Seth Eliot</h2>


<p>
<a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/b/seliot/archive/2010/04/21/what-is-an-sdet-part-2.aspx">Seth Eliot&#8217;s blog on MSDN</a> was particularly useful for both developers and recruiters because it gave a concise and insightful summary:
</p>


<p><em></p>

<h3>What is an SDE-T?</h3>


<ul>
  <li>Programming experience a must
  <ul>
    <li>Key here is that the candidate is a Developer. Strong QA candidates without development experience are generally not acceptable for this role.</li>
  </ul>
  </li>
</ul>


<ul>
  <li>Test Automation
    <ul>
      <li>Writing code to test code: UI and API level testing</li>
    </ul>
    <ul>
    <li>Creating, modifying, or designing test frameworks</li>
    </ul>
    <ul>
      <li>Good: Selenium, JUnit, NUnit, TestNG, etc.</li>
    </ul>
    <ul>
      <li>Using &ldquo;canned&rdquo; products like QuickTest Pro, TestDirector, SilkTest is generally *not* sufficient</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>


<ul>
  <li>SDLC and Software Processes
    <ul>
      <li>Agile/Scrum a plus</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>


<ul>
  <li>QA interest / enthusiasm / experience
    <ul>
      <li>Created Test Cases, Test Plans</li>
      <li>Debug / troubleshoot issues that they found (deep dive)</li>
      <li>Bug reporting / triage / prioritization</li>
      <li>Was responsible for guiding quality on production release</li>
      <li>Functional, load, stress, user interaction testing</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>


<ul>
  <li>Customer focus
    <ul>
      <li>Customer facing experience a plus</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>


<ul>
  <li>&#8220;Soft&#8221; Skills 
    <ul>
      <li>Communication </li>
      <li>Driving consensus </li>
      <li>Leadership </li>
      <li>Creativity</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>


<ul>
  <li>Technologies 
    <ul>
      <li>Must have experience programming a high-level OO language (C#, Java, C++, or C#) 
        <ul>
          <li>C#/.NET experience highly preferred</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
    <ul>
      <li>RDBMS, SQL, stored procedures. SQL Server preferred. </li>
      <li>Web technologies: HTML, JavaScript, web services, XML, CSS</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>


<h3>How to sell the SDE-T role to a developer</h3>


<ul>
  <li>Breadth of experience over narrow focus </li>
  <li>End to end product expertise. From development to user interaction </li>
  <li>Subject Matter Expert on product. Has input on product direction. </li>
  <li>Career &ldquo;big fish in a small pond&rdquo;&hellip; a strong contributor can really make a name for him or herself. Easier than in Dev because do not get &ldquo;pigeon holed&rdquo; and because the QA field is more exclusive.</li>
</ul>


<p></em></p>

<p><strong><em>This guest blog post is by Pradeep Chauhan, Founder of <a href="http://www.oncontracting.com">OnContracting.com</a>.
<a href="http://www.oncontracting.com">OnContracting.com</a> is an online community and marketplace that helps professionals find temporary contract jobs at great local companies by giving them access to hard to find information and helping them connect with the best recruiters to get those jobs.
</em></strong></a>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What Makes a Strong Recruiting Team]]></title>
    <link href="http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/02/01/what-makes-a-strong-recruiting-team/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-01T22:26:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/02/01/what-makes-a-strong-recruiting-team</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In order to attract top talent to your organization it is imperative that you have a top-notch recruiting team in place. I often wonder if organizations realize just how important recruiting is to the success of an organization. If an organization does not have the very best recruiting team in place, it can be at a severe competitive disadvantage. The recruiting function is the key driving force in ensuring the right hires made and less than desirable hires are avoided.</p>


<!--More-->


<p>I felt the need to write this piece because I think organizations need to focus more time and effort on assessing potential recruiters. Organizations need to move beyond seeing the recruiter as someone who solely serves a transactional purpose and instead view the recruiter as someone who can have a powerful transformational impact.</p>


<p>Over the years I have heard candidates tell me one recruiting nightmare after another and it has pained me to hear these stories.  I myself have also had some less than favorable recruiting experiences and from these experiences I have learned what not to do as a recruiter.</p>


<p>On a positive note, I have had the opportunity to both work with, and learn from, some truly amazing recruiters. Compiling all of these experiences and data points helped me devise this list of traits I think are important to consider when assessing potential recruiters for your team.</p>


<p>1)      <strong>Hire individuals who are more than mere resume pushers</strong> – Resume pushers send large numbers of resumes to hiring managers without even bothering to screen the candidates. The hiring manager is then left having to do all the work. When a recruiter is a resume pusher, they are not doing his/her job and are definitely not a value-add to the organization. The best recruiters serve as consultants or partners to the business. These recruiters perform due diligence in sourcing candidates, screening candidates, and providing in-depth candidates summaries to hiring managers. If recruiters are consultants versus resume pushers, they will be respected by both candidates and hiring managers.</p>


<p>2)      <strong>Hire individuals who will be evangelists for your organization</strong> – If a recruiter isn’t excited about working for your organization, how can the recruiter get a candidate excited, or at least interested in working for your organization? Candidates often ask the question, “Why should I work for this organization?” If a recruiter can’t give a genuine enthusiastic answer for this question to candidates, you don’t have the right recruiter on-board. As a recruiter you should be able to easily sell your organization to a candidate. You should truly believe in the statement, “I love working for this organization! This is the best organization to work for because of X, Y, Z reasons.”</p>


<p>3)      <strong>Hire recruiters with a competitive spirit – </strong>The very best recruiters are extremely driven and have a strong desire to win. Recruiting can be quite competitive, especially when dealing with highly desirable candidates. As a recruiter at Microsoft I often compete against companies such as Amazon and Google for top talent. When a candidate informed me he or she was also in process with some of these big name players, I get an adrenaline rush because I knew securing the candidate will be a challenge. If recruiters lack this inner competitiveness, they may just allow top candidates to slip away without doing everything in their power to get the candidate.</p>


<p>4)      <strong>Hire hunters versus farmers – </strong>In order to hire top talent for your organization, you need recruiters who will do more than just wait for candidates to submit their resumes on-line. The best candidates are often passive candidates. In order to find these passive candidates, recruiters must go on the hunt for these candidates by cold calling, networking, sourcing, and maintaining long-term relationships with candidates. If recruiters just sit back and wait for resumes to come along, they are missing out on potential A+ candidates.</p>


<p>5)      <strong>Hire individuals who can serve as consultants to the business – </strong>At Microsoft I work with some of the most talented and successful recruiters I have ever met. The reason these recruiters stand out is because they know the business and, as a result, hiring managers and candidates respect them. In order for recruiters to be true consultants, they need to take the time to learn the business. This means spending time learning from hiring managers, reading up on the business, attending presentations, and analyzing the strengths and weaknesses of competitors in the same market.</p>


<p>6)      <strong>Hire individuals who are passionate about recruiting – </strong>When recruiters are passionate about what they do, they often go above and beyond in their jobs. Actually passionate recruiters don’t even see recruiting as a job, they see recruiting as something they love to do, whether they are working or not. The passionate recruiters I have encountered have this positive energy that is contagious. You just know they are successful because of a love for what they do.</p>


<p><strong>7)      </strong><strong>Hire individuals with a high level of emotional intelligence – </strong>Individuals with a high level of emotional intelligence standout because they can easily build relationships with just about anyone. From my experience, recruiting is all about relationship building, both with candidates and hiring managers. Individuals with a high EQ tend to figure out how to connect with people on a personal level, which helps tremendously when you are trying to fully assess someone’s fit for an organization and a specific role within the organization. A high EQ serves a recruiter well because it gives a person an ability to see beyond the obvious and use strong intuition and other soft skills to provide additional feedback on candidates.<strong></strong></p>


<p><strong> </strong><strong>8)      </strong><strong>Hire courageous individuals – </strong>The best recruiters I have met are willing to stand up for their decisions about candidates, even if the rest of the interview team disagrees with them. As a recruiter, it’s important you have an opinion and are willing to make a case for it. You may not always be right, but at least you had the courage to stand by your decision. Also, when it comes to negotiating offers with candidates, a recruiter needs to be confident and firm. If there is no flexibility with the offer and the candidate is pushing back, the recruiter needs to inform the candidate, “This is the very best offer for these reasons.” <strong></strong></p>


<p><strong> 9</strong><strong>) Hire strong communicators – </strong>As a recruiter, your primary responsibility is to communicate regularly with your candidates and hiring managers. Early on in my career, a former boss once said it’s always best to err on the side of over communicating. This advice has stuck with me throughout my career and I am grateful to have received it. My rule of thumb is to never allow more than a week to pass without providing an update to candidates and hiring managers. I have heard of recruiters never getting back to candidates after on-site interviews. Here a candidate takes time off work, possibly even flies to another state for the interview, then never hears the results of the interview. Whether or not you have good news, bad news, or no news, it is your job to keep an ongoing dialogue with candidates and hiring managers. Top-notch recruiters are proactive in their communications and never keep the candidates and hiring managers wondering what is going on.</p>




<p><strong><em> Colleen Canney is a Technical Recruiter and Career Coach based in Seattle, WA. For more information on Colleen, please visit her website at: </em></strong><a href="http://www.colleencanney.com">www.colleencanney.com</a>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Job Description Review by Developers - QA Engineer]]></title>
    <link href="http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/01/29/job-description-review-by-developer-qa-engineer/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-29T11:56:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/01/29/job-description-review-by-developer-qa-engineer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>QA Engineer - Desktop Virtualization (Seattle)</h2>


<p>
In this series, I invite someone to review a real job description with matching or related technical background.  In these reviews, you&#8217;ll learn the unfiltered feedback and thoughts from the technical people who are the target readers of these job descriptions.  Please note: each review reflects only the opinion of the specific reviewer.
</p>


<!-- More -->


<p><strong>Please give us your career summary.</strong></p>


<p>
My expertise and interests
<ul>
<li>Mobile development</li>
<li>Startup environment</li>
<li>Multi-media</li>
<li>Monetization techniques</li>
</ul>
</p>


<p>My past experience includes</p>

<ul>
<li>QA engineering team building</li>
<li>Windows development</li>
<li>Mac application development</li>
<li>7 years at MS Windows group</li>
</ul>




<p><strong>
What type of jobs are you looking for today? How is it different from your last job?
</strong></p>




<p>
I am looking for positions as such Engineering Manager or Product Manager.  I want to work in a smaller environment because of the variety of work, opportunity to learn, and ability to switch roles (such as from engineering to product management).  What is very important to me is super low barrier to communication and learning.  By this I mean I can easily interact with other roles on the team and within the company.
</p>




<p><strong>
How do you go about conducting your job search?
</strong></p>


<p>
I use Craigslist.  Three of my previous jobs were found via Craigslist.  This time I interviewed for a position at Amazon because of their Craigslist posting.  I didn’t look elsewhere.
</p>




<p><strong>
Why do you like using Craigslist?
</strong></p>


<p>
I feel company websites are too narrow.  I want to see the overall job market and the variety on Craigslist can give me a better idea.  Craigslist is most convenient for me and it has enough positions that I’m interested in, so I don’t feel the need to use job boards or LinkedIn.
</p>


<p>
The reason I don’t use job board or LinkedIn is because
<ol>
<li>Creating accounts at different job boards is a hassle</li>
<li>I’m concerned about privacy and security issues (i.e. my search/view history might be shown).</li>
</ol>
</p>


<p><strong>
How do you find job postings online?
</strong></p>


<p>
I don’t use any keyword search.  I go to Craigslist to scan for interesting items.  Even though I’m looking for engineering manager level positions, I will look at jobs at companies that are doing interesting work.  Then I will go to that company’s own career site to find out more.
</p>


<p><strong>
Let’s find a job description.  Please tell me what comes to your mind.
</strong></p>


<p>
Okay, let’s go to Craigslist.  The top job posting happens to be a QA role, which matches my background.
</p>


<p>
(After about 20 seconds scanning this job description)  Here are the three things that stand out for me:
</p>


<p><img src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/3131770/QA_JD.png" title="What Stands Out" ></p>

<p>
<ol>
<li>Virtual Machine Engine: It&#8217;s an interesting technology to me.</li>
<li>Virtualization and Coding Theory: Once again, I&#8217;m interested in the technology.</li>
<li>Company info: It&#8217;s good to know the company is profitable, have lots of users and the type of users the company has.</li>
</ol>
</p>


<p>
Everything else is just standard stuff and is pretty boring.
</p>


<p><strong>
Please rate this job description.
</strong></p>


<p>My overall rating: Average of below average - nothing too exciting.</p>


<p><strong>
Interest-level heat map of this job description for this engineer:</strong>
(Yellow - interesting.  Grey - not interesting.)
</p>


<p><img src="https://dl.dropbox.com/u/3131770/QA_JD_overall.png" title="Developer Interest Heat Map" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developer Mind Reading 101]]></title>
    <link href="http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/01/24/developer-mind-reading-101/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-24T23:37:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/01/24/developer-mind-reading-101</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>What Developers Look for in a Job</h2>


<p>
If you’re a technical recruiter, knowing what’s on your candidate’s mind helps tremendously at every step of your interaction with them.  The better you know what the most important considerations are on their mind, the better chance you have to successfully recruit them.  Here is a list of super power you’ll get when you can “read mind” - <!-- More -->
   <ul>
     <li>
       Having developers return your email or phone call during your initial reach out
     </li>
     <li>
       Sustaining your candidate’s interest level while going through all the testing, qualifying, and interviewing
     </li>
     <li>
       Reaching a win-win outcome during the offer negotiation to bring them on board
     </li>
   </ul>
<p>

<h3>What developers tell you</h3>
<p>
  It turns out this is a hot topic among technical people as well.  Whenever I talk to my fellow developers/engineers, I get many eager responses.  Here is a (long) list of typical answers you’ll get when you ask technical people what they are looking for:
  <ul>
    <li>I like to wear many hats</li>
    <li>No bureaucracy</li>
    <li>A place where I can build something awesome</li>
    <li>I want no politics</li>
    <li>I have ownership in the product</li>
    <li>What I do and how hard I work actually matters</li>
    <li>I have responsible for things that are above my pay grade</li>
    <li>The harder I work, the faster I grow and become rewarded</li>
    <li>I want to be self-directed</li>
    <li>I need a sense of purpose</li>
    <li>I want become even better in what I do</li>
    <li>The team I will work with is important</li>
    <li>I want to solve an important problem (ex: technical challenges, or solves a personal pain point, etc)</li>
    <li>I’m looking for the *opportunity* to make a lot of money via options/equity is exciting</li>
    <li>I’d like to play a key role in defining product/strategy (personal voice and influence)</li>
    <li>I want the right title/role/responsibilities</li>
    <li>I am looking for a sense of freedom (e.g., escape bigger company politics/inefficiencies, more flexibility in schedule, etc)</li>
    <li>Experience (experiential learning, connections, etc) that can lead me to a bigger career goal is important</li>
    <li>Company culture/environment matters a lot</li>
    <li>I am looking for a collaborative environment</li>
    <li>I need variety in my work so I won’t be bored</li>
    <li>The opportunity to be shaping the technical landscape of a product excites me</li>
    <li>I want to be an early engineer at a famous company</li>
  </ul>
</p>

<h3>What they are REALLY saying</h3>
<p>
With a list this long, it’s difficult to keep all these in your head when you interact with your candidates.  The good news is that we can boil them down into four simple categories:
  <ol>
    <li>People
      <ul>
        <li>I want to be belong to a league of smart people</li>
        <li>I want them to like me and recognize my ability and contribution</li>
        <li>I want to learn from smart people I work with and become even smarter</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Work
      <ul>
        <li>I want stimulating and challenging work</li>
        <li>I need to find meaning in my work and see my work make an impact</li>
        <li>I also want to do work that will increase my market value even more</li>
        <li>I want to be constantly learning new technologies and gaining skills</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Reward
      <ul>
        <li>I like to see a direct correlation between effort and reward</li>
        <li>Furthermore, I’m excited about the chance of hitting the “jackpot” by joining the next Facebook</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
    <li>Autonomy
      <ul>
        <li>The company trust me to make decisions, from technical decisions to my work schedule</li>
      </ul>
    </li>
  </ol>
</p>

<h3>How to use it in your recruiting</h3>
  <p>
Now when we look at this summary, we can see that technical people – developers, software engineers, designers, QA engineers, database architect, DevOps, PMs, etc. – want pretty much the same thing as everyone else.  The difference is that good technical candidates are in a position to choose, so they set the bar pretty high.  This means they expect to find a job that meets ALL of their criteria, because they can.
  </p>
  <p>
Now you knowing the main decision factors of technical talent, incorporate these into all your interactions with your candidates when you recruit them.  For example, saying something like
</p>
<blockquote><p>“In our Big Data SDE role, you get to play with petabytes of data, code up mind-bending machine learning algorithms, and become a master of all things Big Data – Cassandra, Hbase, PIG, Hive, Hadoop, and more.”</p></blockquote>
<p>is a lot more enticing than saying</p>
<blockquote><p>“I have a very good job opportunity. I am attaching the job description. If you are interested, kindly send your updated resume.”</p></blockquote>
  <p>
Intrigue your candidates by mapping the job requirements to what they look for in a job.  When you incorporate this into every piece of communication, your candidates will become a lot more enthusiastic and cooperative.
  </p>

<h3>Getting to a successful hire</h3>
  <p>
These are the basic requirements developers have in their next job.  Be sure you address at least 90%, if not all, of them.   To go beyond the basics, you need to also learn about each candidate’s unique situation.  That’s where the more subjective requirements come into consideration.  Additionally, knowing how your candidates rank their decision factors will be crucial during the negotiation.  These will be in a future blog, “Developer Mind Reading 202.”
  </p>
  <br/>
  <p>
Do you have other items or recruiting stories you’d like to share?  Please let us know.
  </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
