<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: technology terms | Geekology - Technical Recruiting Training]]></title>
  <link href="http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/categories/technology-terms/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://geekology.heroku.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-04-18T12:41:06-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://geekology.heroku.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geekology]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[geekology@jobfully.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Geek Language Quiz - 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/04/18/geek-language-quiz-1/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-18T11:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://geekology.heroku.com/blog/2013/04/18/geek-language-quiz-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>
In this <em>"Geek Language Quiz"</em> series, we'll list some commonly asked questions about technical terms, especially for recruiting purposes, and their answers.  Test and score yourself on your understanding of the Geek language.  Have fun!
</p>


<!-- More -->


<p>
<em>Q. How are Java and JavaScript related?</em>
</br>
<em>A. </em>They are not at all related.  Java is an general-purpose programming language.  JavaScript is most commonly used for interacting with end users, such as in a web application users see in a browser.
</p>




<p>
<em>Q. What is so-called Open Source Software?</em>
</br>
<em>A. </em>Open Source Software, as opposed to Closed Source or Proprietary Software, is computer software with its source code made available and licensed with an open-source license in which the copyright holder provides the rights to study, change and distribute the software for free to anyone and for any purpose.
</p>




<p>
<em>Q. What’s the difference between SDE and SDET?</em>
</br>
<em>A. </em>
SDE stands for Software Development Engineer.  SDET stands for Software Development Engineer in Test.  Both roles are software developers.  SDEs write code for software systems that will be used by the target end users.  SDETs write code to automate testing against software systems SDEs created and to identify and report defects (i.e. bugs).
</p>




<p>
<em>Q. Are UI and UX the same or different?</em>
</br>
<em>A. </em>
UX (i.e. user experience) is the overall experience one has with a product or service. UI (i.e. user interface) is typically a combination of visual design (the look and feel) and the interaction design (how it works). UI can be a component of UX, but many user experiences don't have UIs.
</p>




<p>
<em>Q. What does “Object-Oriented Programming” mean?</em>
</br>
<em>A. </em>
Object-oriented programming (OOP) is a programming paradigm that represents concepts as "objects" with nouns (data) and verbs (actions).  The main benefit of using Object-Oriented Programming is that it's one way of breaking complex problems into more manageable ones.
</p>




<p>
<em>Q. What kind of architecture does a software architect build?</em>
</br>
<em>A. </em>
Software architecture is not a well-defined term, even among the software engineering community.  To date, there is still no agreement on the precise definition of software architecture.  One way to define software architecture is a roadmap that defines the strategic software design decisions, based on known constraints and requirements.
</p>




<p>
Please use the Comments below or email <em>geekology@jobfully.com</em> to let us know if there are questions you wish to see in the <em>"Geek Language Quiz"</em> series.  We'd love to hear from you.
</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
